Guide to the Nancy Dean Papers, 1950-2017
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Nancy Dean Papers
1950-2017
Dean, Nancy
6.5 cubic feet (20 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Collection includes manuscripts of Dean’s scholarly works, fiction and theatrical writing, as well as subject files and teaching files. Collection includes correspondence with friends and family, handwritten notes and manuscript drafts, as well as index cards containing notes used for research and/or teaching. Publicity and press clippings files include reviews of Dean’s theatrical works. Collection also contains audio visual materials, including CDs, DVDs, as well as audio and video cassettes.
Biographical Note
Nancy Dean (1930-2017), was an scholar of medieval history and literature specializing in Chaucer, professor, playwright, author of fiction, plays and opera, and noted advocate and philanthropist for LGBTQ causes. She founded the Astraea Foundation, which supports the needs of lesbians and women of color. With Beva Eastman, her partner of 54 years, she went on to create the Open Meadows Foundation, a global fund supporting political change directed by and benefiting women and girls. A Vassar alumna (VC Class of 1952), Dean received a masters degree from Radcliffe (1953), a PhD in Medieval Studies from New York University (1963), followed by a 28-year teaching career at Hunter College (1963-1991), teaching Medieval Studies, Chaucer, Creative Writing and Women’s Studies). Before teaching at Hunter, Dean taught at the American College for Girls in Istanbul, Turkey for three years during the 1950s.
Published works by Dean include: In the Mind of the Writer (Cranfield Press), In the Looking Glass: Twenty-one modern short stories by women, (Putnam Press, 1977), and published short stories in periodicals including Room with a View (The Gathering) and IKON (Requited Love). Her first novel entitled Anna’s Country, was written and published under the pseudonym, Elizabeth Lang (Naiad Press, 1981). Playscripts include: Larks and Owls (1986), Returning Home (1989), Hetty Pepper’s Stew (1986), Blood and Water (1986), Ophelia’s Laughter (1988), Ripe Avocados (2008), Gloria’s Visit (1990), Which Marriage? (1991), Burning Bridges (1992), Upstairs? In the Afternoon? (1995), and That Ilk (1998).
Excerpts from her libretto Criseyde, a feminist reading of Chaucer’s Troilus and Criseyde, were presented in Middle English at performance staged at City University of New York in 2008. Dean was a member of both the Dramatists Guild and the Women Playwrights Collective.
Scope and Content Note
Manuscripts, many in draft form, comprise the majority of the collection, documenting Dean’s academic work from Vassar undergraduate studies through graduate and PhD work at Radcliffe and New York University. Included among these is Dean’s PhD dissertation, Studies in Chaucer’s Use of Ovid in Selected Early Poems. Speech and lecture files include talks given at Vassar, Allegheny College, Hunter College, Brooklyn College and Smith College. Playscripts and opera librettos, both in draft and final form are also included among her writings. Playscript files also include some correspondence, editorial notations, contracts, agreements, and program notes. Manuscript files for dramatic works contain scripts, research notes, correspondence, musical scores, and publicity.
Dean’s correspondence files include both professional and personal communication. Of note are letters written to both her mother and father during her years teaching in Turkey during the 1950s.
Teaching and subject files document Dean’s management of her career as both a writer and college professor. A collection of oversized index cards contain notes used for researching and/or teaching 17th & 18th century literature. Teaching files also contain class schedules, notes, bibliographies and syllabi. Audio visual material includes CDs, DVDs, and audio and video tapes documenting selections from Dean’s theatrical works including a recording of Dean reading the libretto of her opera, Criseyde.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Hunter College--Faculty; Vassar College--Alumni and alumnae; Vassar College--Students
Subjects:
Women college teachers--United States; Women dramatists--United States; Women novelists--United States
Document Types:
Manuscripts (documents)
VCL Categories
LGBTQ (Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual,Transgender & Queer) Life and Culture; Literature and Writing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, July 2019. Updated by Mark Seidl, September 2020.
Acquisition Information
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into eight series. Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically, by title. Writings are arranged into subseries by name by of teaching institution, and by genre (fiction and playscripts), as arranged by the author. Subject and teaching files are arranged alphabetically, as titled by the creator.
Series List
- Series I. Subject Files, approximately 1952-2011; (Box 1-2)
- Series II. Teaching Files, 1988, undated; (Box 3-6, 19)
- Series III. Writings, approximately 1974-2000; (Box 7-15)
- Series IV. Correspondence, 1951-2009; (Box 16-17)
- Series V. Speeches and Lectures, approximately 1976-2011; (Box 18)
- Series VI. Publicity and Press clippings, 1977-2008; (Box 18-19)
- Series VII. Photographs, approximately 1956-2000; (Box 18)
- Series VIII. Audiovisual Material, approximately 1967-2008; (Box 20)
Container List
- SERIES I. SUBJECT FILES, approximately 1952-2011
  - Actor's Alliance, 1989-1992 (1.1-1.3)
  - Astrea Foundation, 1979-2009 (19.2)
  - Bio file, certificates, awards, 1982-2009 (1.4)
  - Bio file, certificates, Vassar, Harvard, New York University, Hunter College, 1952-1999 (20.1)
  - Bio file, resumes, artist statements, 1976-2003 (1.5)
  - Collected bibliographies, feminist writings, undated (1.6)
  - Criseyde, opera, character studies, 2011 (1.7)
  - Criseyde, opera, copyright certification, 2009-2010 (1.8)
  - The Crystal Quilt, publicity, 1993 (1.9)
  - Hunter College, Future Speak, 1982 (1.10)
  - Hunter College Annual Report, Asst. Dean of Instruction, 1967-1968 (1.11)
  - Hunter College, resume, teaching file, memos, 1963-1982 (1.12)
  - International Women Playwrights Conference, 1991-1997 (1.13)
  - Intimate Acts: Eight Contemporary Lesbian Plays, 1996-2000 (1.14-1.15)
  - Lesbian Theater Project, 1996-1997 (1.16)
  - Love Creek Productions, 1986-2008 (1.17)
  - Manhattan Repertory Theatre, 2009 (1.18)
  - Medieval Club, 1967-1971 (2.1)
  - Medieval Literature, 1974-1987 (2.2)
  - New York University, reference/teaching, 1960-1985 (2.3)
  - Open Meadows Foundation, press releases, newsletters, 1986-1992 (2.4)
  - Pen and Brush Playwrights Conference, 1996-2004 (2.5-2.9)
  - Play agreements, requests, 1992-2001 (2.10)
  - That Ilk, play, correspondence, press, agreements, 1998-2000 (2.11)
  - Vassar, Smashing History: 150 Years of LGBTQA, speech text, logistical file, 2001-2011 (2.12)
  - Women's One World Theater, play, Upstairs in the Afternoon, 1996 (2.13)
- SERIES II. TEACHING FILES, 1988, undated
  - 17th, 18th Century Literature, index cards (notes), undated (3.1-3.6, 4.1-4.6, 19.3)
  - Chaucer: The Early Works, class bibliography, 1988 (4.7)
  - Chaucer, index cards (notes), undated (5.1-5.6, 6.1-6.6)
  - Teaching tool, timeline, Anglo Saxon Period, undated (19.4)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS, approximately 1950-2015
  - General
    - Book of Duchess, undated; (manuscript and typescritp) (7.1)
    - Book proposal, Anthology of Visions of the 1990s, 1988-1989 (7.2-7.3)
    - Book proposal, The Best Stories By American Women, 1987-1989 (7.4)
    - Book proposal, Women, According to Women: Twenty One Short Stories, 1977-1980 (7.5)
    - Chaucer's Complaint, A Genre Descended from the Heroides, Comparative Literature, 1967; (offprint) (7.6)
    - Chaucer's House of Fame, first draft, with edits, bibliography, 1978; (notes) (7.7-7.10)
    - Chaucer and Ovid, introduction, undates; (edited typescript) (7.11)
    - Chaucer's Use of Myth, 1968 (7.12)
    - Criseyde, 2005 (7.13)
    - Criseyde, opera, full musical score, 2010 (19.5-19.7)
    - Criseyde, opera libretto, 2001 (8.1)
    - Criseyde, opera, piano and vocal score, 2008 (8.2)
    - Criseyde, opera, scene list, 2006 (8.3)
    - Criseyde, An Opera in Three Acts, Being a Feminist Retelling of Chaucer's Troilus and Criseyde, libretto, undated (8.4)
    - Ecloga Theoduli, 1970-1971; (typescript) (8.5-8.6)
    - Ecloga Theoduli, What School Child Might Have Learned from the Ecloga Theoduli, 1972-1973; (typescript) (8.7)
    - The Gatherings, by Elizabeth Lang [Nancy Dean], 1976; (includes edits) (8.8)
    - Ladies Mile, TS, 2012; (typescript; includes corresposdence) (8.9)
    - Nun's Priest's Tale, 1971-1974; (typescript) (8.10)
    - Ovid's Elegies From Exile, Chaucer's Book III, House of Fame, 1964; (typescript) (8.11)
    - Poetry, 1953-1975; (manbuscripts, notes) (9.1-9.3)
    - Requited Love, Ikon Press, undated; (typescript) (9.4)
    - Song to David Chretien Yvain, 1961, 1971; (includes notes, correspondence) (9.5-9.6)
    - Submitted/Unpublished fiction, 1950-1970; (typescripts) (10.1-10.3)
    - Three Voices, One Song, 1999-2000; (typescript) (10.4-10.6)
  - Fiction
    - Essays, short stories, 1970-1990; (typescripts) (10.7-10.10)
    - Murder on the Mantel, 1986; (typescript) (10.11-10.12, 11.1-11.4)
  - Playscripts
    - Blood and Water, 1988-2008 (11.5)
    - Burning Bridges, 2010 (11.6)
    - The Cooky Thief, 1998 (11.7)
    - Counter Talk, 1999 (11.8)
    - Gloria's Visit, 1990 (11.9)
    - Hetty Pepper's Stew, 1987, 2008 (11.10)
    - High Buttoned Sneakers: The Bartow Pell Staircase, 2009 (11.11)
    - Larks and Owls, 1984-1986 (11.12)
    - The Misanthrope, undated (11.13-11.14)
    - Murder at the Regatta, 1998 (12.1-12.2)
    - Ophelia, 2004-2015 (12.3)
    - Ophelia's Laughter, 1988 (12.4)
    - Ophelia's Rainbows, undated (12.5)
    - Resort, 2002 (12.6)
    - Returning Home, 1988 (12.7)
    - Ripe Avocados, 2001-2005 (12.8)
    - That Ilk, 1987-2000 (12.9)
    - Upstairs in the Afternoon, 1995-1996 (12.10)
    - Which Marriage?, undated; (typescript) (12.11)
    - The Yellow Wallpaper, based on a short story by Charlotte Perkins Gilman, undated (12.12)
  - Harvard University
    - Miscellaneous academic papers, 1952-1953 (13.1)
  - Hunter College
    - How Were Medieval School Children Introduced to Myths, 1973 (13.2)
    - The Complaints of Machaut and Chaucer, 1962, 1983; (typescripts) (13.3-13.7)
  - New York University
    - Bibliography, Titus Andronicus, 1959; (typescript) (13.8)
    - Chaucer, 1960; (typescript) (13.9)
    - Chaucer's Use of Ovid, 1960; (typescript) (13.10-13.11)
    - Dissertation Abstract, Studies in Chaucer's Use of Ovid, 1961-1966 (13.12)
    - Dissertation, PhD, Studies in Chaucer's Use of Ovid in Selected Early Poems, 1963 (14.1-14.6)
    - Dryden, Pope, Swift, Chaucer (final exam), 1960; (typescript) (14.7)
    - Dryden, Pope, Shakespeare, Milton, 1960-1961; (typescript, notes) (14.8-14.10)
    - Milton: An Explication of Sonnet XI, 1960 (14.11)
    - Richard Coeur de Lion, 1961; (manuscript, typescript) (15.1-15.4)
    - The Wife of Bath, 1960; (typescript) (15.5)
    - The Use of Ovid's Tale Seyx and Alcyone, 1960 (19.8)
  - Vassar College
    - Chaucer, 1950; (typescript) (15.6)
    - Preaching in Chaucer's Time, 1950; (edited typescript) (15.7)
    - Vassar Alumnae Magazine, October 1967 (15.8)
  - Other Writings
    - Ginnie Goddard on Nancy Dean, Contemporary Lesbian Writers, 1991-1994 (15.9-15.10)
- SERIES IV. CORRESPONDENCE, 1951-2017
  - Professional
    - From Nancy Dean, 1951, 1956 (16.1)
    - To Nancy Dean, from friends/associates, 1951-1999 (16.2-16.3)
    - To/From Nancy Dean, re: Criseyde, opera logistics, 2003-2009 (16.4-16.10)
    - Re: In the Mind of the Writer, published work, 1972-1973 (16.11)
    - Re: Playwriting, 1991-2000 (16.12-16.13)
    - Re: Teaching, Vassar, Hunter, NYU, Turkey, 1958-2017 (16.14-16.16)
  - Personal
    - From Dean, Archie [father], 1951-1971 (17.1)
    - From Dean, Ella Lang [mother], 1952-1962 (17.2)
    - From Nancy Dean to parents, 1956-1962 (17.3-17.10)
- SERIES V. SPEECHES/LECTURES, approximately 1976-2011
  - All Lesbian Theater is Political, Allegheny College, 1997 (18.1)
  - Barnard College - The Scholar and the Feminist Towards a Politics of Sexualtiy, 1982 (18.2)
  - Brooklyn College, Women's Studies Association Conference, Culture and Change, 1984 (18.3)
  - CUNY Conference, Working Towards Multiculturalism, 1991 (18.4)
  - Draddy Lecture, Hunter College, Social Change and the English Language, 1989 (18.5)
  - The Female Man, Women's Studies, undated; (edited typescript (18.6)
  - Hunter College Women's Studies, Setting the Record Straight, 1996 (18.7)
  - Memorial, Elizabeth Evans, 1995 (18.8)
  - Modern Language Association, Feminist Short Stories, New Forms and Styles, 1976 (18.9)
  - New York Women's Association, The Ending of Woman On Edge of Time, 1984 (18.10)
  - On Late Bloomers, The Crystal Quilt, 1994 (18.11)
  - Smith College, interview transcript, 2004 (18.12)
  - Spyer, Thea-memorial, 2009 (18.13)
  - Vassar College, Smashing 150 Years of LGBTIQA at Vassar, To Be a Freshman in 1948, 2011 (18.14)
  - Writing at Hunter College, Conference, 1996 (18.15)
- SERIES VI. PUBLICITY/PRESS CLIPPINGS, 1977-2008
  - Anna's Country, by Elizabeth Lang [Nancy Dean], 1981-1991 (18.16)
  - Blood and Water, one act play, 1988 (18.17)
  - Criseyde, opera program, City Opera, CUNY, 2008 (18.18)
  - In the Looking Glass, edited by Nancy Dean and Myra Stark, 1977-1979 (19.1)
  - Women's Theatre Collective, 1985-1999 (18.19)
- SERIES VII. PHOTOGRAPHS, approximately 1956-2000
  - Portrait, Nancy Dean, undated (18.20)
  - Publicity photos, That Ilk production, 19980-2000 (18.21)
  - Photographic prints separated from correspondence, family/friends, 1956-1962 (18.22)
- SERIES VIII. AUDIO/VISUAL MATERIALS, approximately 1967-2008
  - Blood and Water, audio cassette, undated (Box 20)
  - Burning Bridges, 1993; (VHS tape) (Box 20)
  - Criseyde, opera, undated; (CD, DVD) (Box 20)
  - Criseyde, Nancy Dean reading libretto, 2008; (CD) (Box 20)
  - Hetty Pepper's Stew, 2008; (CD) (Box 20)
  - Iliad, Anthony Quayle, undated; (audio cassette) (Box 20)
  - Ripe Avocados, 2008; (CD) (Box 20)
  - Sounds of Chaucer's English, Knapp and Snortum, 1967; (audio cassette) (Box 20)
  - That Ilk, music and voice cues, undated; (CD) (Box 20)